<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>NumFOCUS Foundation</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/feeds/gina-helfrich.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/</id><updated>2015-11-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>NumFOCUS Announces New Fiscally Sponsored Project: NumPy</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2015/11/19/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-numpy/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Gina Helfrich</name></author><id>tag:numfocus.github.io,2015-11-19:numfocus.org/news/2015/11/19/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-numpy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="NumPy" src="/media/img/projects/NumPY.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is pleased to announce &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.numpy.org/"&gt;NumPy&lt;/a&gt; as our newest fiscally sponsored project. NumPy is the fundamental package for scientific computing with Python. It is open source, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BSD&lt;/span&gt;-licensed and contains among other&amp;nbsp;things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a powerful N-dimensional array&amp;nbsp;object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sophisticated (broadcasting)&amp;nbsp;functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tools for integrating C/C++ and Fortran&amp;nbsp;code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;useful linear algebra, Fourier transform, and random number&amp;nbsp;capabilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides its obvious scientific uses, NumPy can also be used as an efficient multi-dimensional container of generic data. Arbitrary data-types can be defined. This allows NumPy to seamlessly and speedily integrate with a wide variety of databases.
With the addition of NumPy, NumFOCUS now fiscally sponsors eleven different open source data science projects. To make a donation to support NumPy or any of NumFOCUS’ other projects, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.org/projects/index.html"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>NumFOCUS Sponsored Project rOpenSci receives $2.9M Award</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2015/11/19/numfocus-sponsored-project-ropensci-receives-29m-award/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Gina Helfrich</name></author><id>tag:numfocus.github.io,2015-11-19:numfocus.org/news/2015/11/19/numfocus-sponsored-project-ropensci-receives-29m-award/</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="rOpenSci" src="/media/img/projects/ropensci_logo.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is pleased to announce that sponsored project &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ropensci.org/"&gt;rOpenSci&lt;/a&gt; has received a grant of nearly $2.9 million over three years from The Leona M. and Harry B. Helmsley Charitable Trust. The grant, which was awarded through the Trust’s Biomedical Research Infrastructure Program, will be used to expand rOpenSci’s mission of developing tools and community around open data and reproducible research practices. Read the full &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ropensci.org/blog/2015/11/19/hemlsley-trust-funding/"&gt;announcement here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make a donation to support rOpenSci or any of NumFOCUS’ other projects, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.org/projects/index.html"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>NumFOCUS Announces New Fiscally Sponsored Project: pandas</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2015/10/09/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-pandas/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Gina Helfrich</name></author><id>tag:numfocus.github.io,2015-10-09:numfocus.org/news/2015/10/09/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-pandas/</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="pandas" src="/media/img/projects/pandas.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is pleased to announce &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pandas.pydata.org/community.html"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt; as our newest fiscally sponsored project. pandas is an open source, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BSD&lt;/span&gt;-licensed library providing high-performance, easy-to-use data structures and data analysis tools for the Python programming&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pandas enables users to carry out their entire data analysis workflow in Python without having to switch to a more domain-specific language like R. Combined with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;IPython&lt;/a&gt; (also a NumFOCUS fiscally sponsored project) and other libraries, the environment for doing data analysis in Python excels in performance, productivity, and the ability to collaborate. Python with pandas is in use in a wide variety of academic and commercial domains, including Finance, Neuroscience, Economics, Statistics, Advertising, Web Analytics, and&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Library&amp;nbsp;Highlights&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fast and efficient DataFrame object for data manipulation with integrated&amp;nbsp;indexing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools for reading and writing data between in-memory data structures and different formats: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSV&lt;/span&gt; and text files, Microsoft Excel, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; databases, and the fast &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intelligent data alignment and integrated handling of missing data: gain automatic label-based alignment in computations and easily manipulate messy data into an orderly&amp;nbsp;form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible reshaping and pivoting of data&amp;nbsp;sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intelligent label-based slicing, fancy indexing, and subsetting of large data&amp;nbsp;sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columns can be inserted and deleted from data structures for size&amp;nbsp;mutability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aggregating or transforming data with a powerful group by engine allowing split-apply-combine operations on data&amp;nbsp;sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High performance merging and joining of data&amp;nbsp;sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hierarchical axis indexing provides an intuitive way of working with high-dimensional data in a lower-dimensional data&amp;nbsp;structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time series-functionality: date range generation and frequency conversion, moving window statistics, moving window linear regressions, date shifting and lagging. Even create domain-specific time offsets and join time series without losing&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highly optimized for performance, with critical code paths written in Cython or&amp;nbsp;C&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the addition of pandas, NumFOCUS now fiscally sponsors ten different open source data science projects. To make a donation to support pandas or any of NumFOCUS’ other projects, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.org/projects/index.html"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>NumFOCUS Announces New Fiscally Sponsored Project: PyTables</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2015/08/31/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-pytables/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Gina Helfrich</name></author><id>tag:numfocus.github.io,2015-08-31:numfocus.org/news/2015/08/31/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-pytables/</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="PyTables" src="/media/img/projects/logo-pytables-small.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is pleased to announce &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pytables.org/"&gt;PyTables&lt;/a&gt; as our newest fiscally sponsored project. PyTables is a package for managing hierarchical datasets designed to efficiently cope with extremely large amounts of&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyTables has been in the Scientific Python ecosystem for well over a decade and has been the front end for data storage for many other projects over the years. PyTables is built on top of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; library, using the Python language and the NumPy package. It features an object-oriented interface that, combined with C extensions for the performance-critical parts of the code (generated using Cython), makes it a fast, yet extremely easy to use tool to interactively browse, process and search very large amounts of data. One important feature of PyTables is that it optimizes memory and disk resources so that data takes up much less space (specially if on-flight compression is used) than other solutions such as relational or object oriented databases. PyTables adoption has grown significantly in recent years as a result of being adopted to implement panda&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF&lt;/span&gt; storage&amp;nbsp;capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyTables can be applied in any scenario where one needs to deal with large datasets,&amp;nbsp;including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Industrial&amp;nbsp;applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data acquisition in real&amp;nbsp;time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality&amp;nbsp;control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast data&amp;nbsp;processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scientific&amp;nbsp;applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meteorology,&amp;nbsp;oceanography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numerical&amp;nbsp;simulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medicine (biological sensors, general data gathering &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;processing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information&amp;nbsp;systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System log monitoring &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;consolidation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tracing of routing&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alert systems in&amp;nbsp;security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PyTables development team members—Anthony Scopatz, Andrea Bedini, Francesc Alted, and Antonio Valentino—are thought leaders in the data science community and have pushed forward new and successful ideas about data parallelism, querying and indexing data, and&amp;nbsp;compression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the addition of PyTables, NumFOCUS now fiscally sponsors nine different open source data science projects. To make a donation to support PyTables or any of NumFOCUS’ other projects, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.org/projects/index.html"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>NumFOCUS Supported Project Data Carpentry Receives Grant</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2015/08/13/numfocus-supported-project-data-carpentry-receives-grant/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Gina Helfrich</name></author><id>tag:numfocus.github.io,2015-08-13:numfocus.org/news/2015/08/13/numfocus-supported-project-data-carpentry-receives-grant/</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="Data Carpentry" src="/media/img/projects/data_carpentry.png" style="height: 150px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is pleased to announce that one of our sponsored projects, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://datacarpentry.org/"&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;, has received $750,000 in funding from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.moore.org"&gt;Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is committed to supporting and promoting world-class, innovative, open source scientific software. A fundamental component of this mission is to develop and provide training that instills good practice, enables scientific progress, and develops a diverse and strong community around open source and open science. We are excited to continue to work with Data Carpentry to grow this community! Also look for Data Carpentry contributors at upcoming &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pydata.org"&gt;PyData&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional information about the activities to be funded by this grant is available at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://datacarpentry.github.io/blog/announce/"&gt;Data Carpentry blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>