<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>NumFOCUS Foundation</title><link>http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/feeds/gina-helfrich.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>NumFOCUS Announces New Fiscally Sponsored Project: PyTables</title><link>http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2015/08/31/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-pytables/</link><description>&lt;img alt="PyTables" src="/media/img/projects/logo-pytables-small.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is pleased to announce &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pytables.org/"&gt;PyTables&lt;/a&gt; as our newest fiscally sponsored project. PyTables is a package for managing hierarchical datasets designed to efficiently cope with extremely large amounts of&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyTables has been in the Scientific Python ecosystem for well over a decade and has been the front end for data storage for many other projects over the years. PyTables is built on top of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; library, using the Python language and the NumPy package. It features an object-oriented interface that, combined with C extensions for the performance-critical parts of the code (generated using Cython), makes it a fast, yet extremely easy to use tool to interactively browse, process and search very large amounts of data. One important feature of PyTables is that it optimizes memory and disk resources so that data takes up much less space (specially if on-flight compression is used) than other solutions such as relational or object oriented databases. PyTables adoption has grown significantly in recent years as a result of being adopted to implement panda&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF&lt;/span&gt; storage&amp;nbsp;capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyTables can be applied in any scenario where one needs to deal with large datasets,&amp;nbsp;including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Industrial&amp;nbsp;applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data acquisition in real&amp;nbsp;time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality&amp;nbsp;control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast data&amp;nbsp;processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scientific&amp;nbsp;applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meteorology,&amp;nbsp;oceanography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numerical&amp;nbsp;simulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medicine (biological sensors, general data gathering &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;processing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information&amp;nbsp;systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System log monitoring &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;consolidation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tracing of routing&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alert systems in&amp;nbsp;security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PyTables development team members—Anthony Scopatz, Andrea Bedini, Francesc Alted, and Antonio Valentino—are thought leaders in the data science community and have pushed forward new and successful ideas about data parallelism, querying and indexing data, and&amp;nbsp;compression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the addition of PyTables, NumFOCUS now fiscally sponsors nine different open source data science projects. To make a donation to support PyTables or any of NumFOCUS’ other projects, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.org/projects/index.html"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Gina Helfrich</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:numfocus.github.io,2015-08-31:numfocus.org/news/2015/08/31/numfocus-announces-new-fiscally-sponsored-project-pytables/</guid></item><item><title>NumFOCUS Supported Project Data Carpentry Receives Grant</title><link>http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2015/08/13/numfocus-supported-project-data-carpentry-receives-grant/</link><description>&lt;img alt="Data Carpentry" src="/media/img/projects/data_carpentry.png" style="height: 150px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is pleased to announce that one of our sponsored projects, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://datacarpentry.org/"&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;, has received $750,000 in funding from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.moore.org"&gt;Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS is committed to supporting and promoting world-class, innovative, open source scientific software. A fundamental component of this mission is to develop and provide training that instills good practice, enables scientific progress, and develops a diverse and strong community around open source and open science. We are excited to continue to work with Data Carpentry to grow this community! Also look for Data Carpentry contributors at upcoming &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pydata.org"&gt;PyData&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional information about the activities to be funded by this grant is available at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://datacarpentry.github.io/blog/announce/"&gt;Data Carpentry blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Gina Helfrich</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:numfocus.github.io,2015-08-13:numfocus.org/news/2015/08/13/numfocus-supported-project-data-carpentry-receives-grant/</guid></item></channel></rss>